Good morning, good morning, good
evening, good afternoon. Welcome to
another episode of Kasar Talk Show.
Uh, I'm going to do randomish. Okay,
random chat. Just random chat. I'm a
computer nerd for 30 years.
And here is my energy drink from Costco.
Wait, why why is the camera not aligned?
So anyway, the energy drink from Costco.
Okay, so this should be a line. But
actually, wait, why is the camera on the
sideways? You know, I think it should be
like that. Oh, because um
anyway, so um that's energy drink from
Costco. And here is my nicotine candy.
By the way, I quit smoking
uh in January called turkey. So that was
amazing. That was fantastic.
But now now and then occasionally I eat
nicotine candy um uh occasionally. So
okay. So if you are here say comment uh
put your comment um there. And today I'm
going to have some drink. Okay. the room
as usual. So, let me switch to my screen
so you can see.
Stop YouTube. Okay. So, show me my
desktop so you can see my window. S talk
show today. It's going to be that I
think we're going to install Rust. Okay.
So, why Rust? Now, if you don't know
Rust programming language, um,
okay, so let me show you. Okay. So,
let's begin to drink. Okay. So, let me
get a drink first.
There it is. As as usual. So, okay. Rum
I discovered. Fantastic. Amazing. Let's
just have a little like two shots.
Okay, that's the first shot. We're going
to have another shot in 20 minutes.
Oh god,
my hand hurts because of the repetitive
strain injury typing too much.
Okay, let's move this to the side like
that.
Okay, so let me show you my programming
stuff. So I'm into programming
languages. So you can see my sudi.info
info uh website and lots of programming
language tutorials I've written in the
past 30 years and let's go to one of
them which uh I talked about the
proliferation of programming languages
okay one of the article you see I
started you know my current project to
learn is F
so I started to write kind of a tutorial
but in this AI age tutorial doesn't mean
anything anymore more because you can
ask AI AI will write a tutorial for you
in one minute you know because I've been
asking AI tremendously like uh 20
questions a day about technical very
computer language design and also the
practical to technical you know so today
I've done a lot JavaScript in this in
past month so anyway so um you can ask a
just write a tutorial in fact I started
in fact I started to accept AI generated
tutorial. So let let me digress. Okay,
let me show you. So if you are here uh
comment okay say something. So let's
see. So you can see go to my
tutorial.info
you go to JavaScript
in depth the best one. Okay. So but you
go to my JavaScript blog. By the way I
named I renamed my webdev blog into
JavaScript blog. So yesterday it was
Kasawa webdev blog. Two mouthful. So now
it's just Casar JavaScript JS block.
Cheers.
Uh can you see can I see uh can you see
me? Can I see myself? Yes. There.
Check.
Video check. Audio check
from room is good.
So you see I named my blog now
JavaScript blog and yesterday we were
doing live stream I was talking about
this task where you want to rename each
of the old blog so that they have from
date and end date. Now it's done. I did
it offline. You see my uh my past blog.
So, but anyway, you go to webdev
tutorial uh JavaScript blog uh and you
see there's a JavaScript evolve
now I you know I start to accept AI
answer so directly I just put AI
generated output on my blog to be sure
they are correct because I manually go
through it uh handcrafted
you know like I I go through it what
word by word and test out all the code.
So it's very good. It's just superb. Uh
for example, JavaScript eval is one of
the more comp complicated thing to write
the tutorial for. You know, you you
can't even write a tutorial even this
even if you are experienced JavaScript
coder. Let's say you've been coding
JavaScript for 10 years. But when it
comes to Eva, you
there's nothing you you really know. I
mean, you can document. You see, you
need to be the JavaScript compiler
writer. That's when you have something
like you you you are able to say what
Eva is actually doing because if you are
just a you know professional coder even
if you used Eva for 10 years there's
nothing much you can say about it except
maybe some experience you see because
Eva is this one of those uh very
technical um kind of advanced thing they
they involve
they are essentially bringing the
programming language age um into your
dynamic runtime environment. Okay. So
even even that concept is a bit more
complex to explain to let's say
beginners let's say you just um you know
start to code you are a teenager I mean
normally anyway so I'm getting
complicated so eval is like so to for a
programming language to have something
like a eval you need to bring the
programming languages passer into the
runtime
runtime environment
Okay, so let me explain. Okay, I'm
digressing over but let me explain.
Okay. So normally you you got you know
programming language you got a compiler
or interpreter that is you know whatever
you type you press run or you know like
uh JavaScript you know deno run or or
golang or whatever f or wam language you
run it the interpreter or the compiler
compiles the code and runs the code.
Okay, that that means it reads what you
have typed and it turns it into the
machine language that the CPU machine
understand and and execute it. Okay, so
that's the compiler or interpreter. The
difference is that the interpreter is
like usually interactive. That's what it
means interpreter. Okay, but if you have
to compile it, usually it's called
compiler. Uh that's like a little
technical difference. Okay.
So but but um so you got this thing
interpreter or compiler turns your code
into a machine language. So the machine
can actually run it. Okay.
Uh now there is a runtime stuff. Now
what is runtime? Runtime is that you
don't have um you know you see runtimes
allows you to run the code. So let's say
you have already a compiled code um
let's see C you need to run it well that
doesn't make s well you know it makes
sense with Java
uh anyway
I'm not I'm not too familiar with this
uh this area okay so but basically
runtime is the environment is a is
environment that that are needed in
order to run the code it may be so for
the if it's compile language it is
you see I'm having difficulty explaining
the concept of runtime because
for compile language such as C or C++
the you know the most common one they
when you compile the code the code
includes the runtime well depends if
compile a fully executable linked and
and what not it comp it it runtime is in
itself but I suppose you can compile
part of C or C++ so so then then that
code won't be able to run by itself okay
uh on the other hand if you are
something like Python the runtime is
just the interpreter okay
anyway so that I I I I don't suppose I'm
doing a good uh job of explaining this
runtime and stuff and I'm digressing
over
but anyway Eva so I needs the parser in
the runtime okay that's one thing it
needs from the like implementation or
technical point of view but on the other
hand from a program programmer's point
of view is allows you to do meta
programming so if Your language have
eval you can eval the your code you can
meaning that you can change your code
dynamically at runtime. So at runtime
you can generate your code you can al or
edit it change it in fact that's what
made this famous okay [snorts]
but anyway so this um anyway so this
getting complicated okay um I don't
think I'm doing a good job about this
meta programming or runtime or the
anyway
but anyways but but for a lot languages
such as JavaScript eva is is one of the
circus thing.
It's circus for many multiple reasons.
Even though it allows you some kind of
meta programming, it does you know you
you you essentially have the full meta
programming capability which is
extremely powerful because it's actually
meta it's meta programming. However, the
way JavaScript has evolved basically
it's uh crippled it. It's like nobody
for one reason it's super slow. Okay,
it's not like really practical
to do meta programming using JavaScript
with eval. Okay, that's one thing. The
other thing is that eval is full of
so-called security problems.
So basically
uh in modern day I mean basically people
don't use eval okay in JavaScript. Now
eval in Python is the same situation.
Now eval in lisp and wuam language
that's entirely different. That's when
you actually do and encourage to do to
use them for meta programming. Okay.
That's lisp and wuam language. Okay.
Am I doing a good job? I don't think so.
And I'm getting boring. I'm bored
myself. Um,
do we have anyone watching?
Okay. So,
let's do something else then. Okay.
So, yeah. Okay. So, we digressed now.
Let's get back. Okay. So, we were
talking about eval. So, I was talking
about finally. So you know I was talking
about how it is eval is one of the
subject in a programming language that
a programmer
have a hard time to write a tutorial
about. Okay. Even if you are experienced
okay unless unless you are the
implementer you know the compiler writer
or you know you implement the
programming language then you can say
you can write a good tutorial about eval
you know how to write so for for for 15
years I don't really have like much to
say about eval whatever I say would be
copy from Mozilla you know copy you know
go to Mozilla got coffee. So I didn't
say much but now with AI
amazing you you know AI in one minute.
So do I have it here some like uh do I I
asked AI like today or yesterday? I
forgot you know somewhere here. Okay
like but I copy the whole thing here. So
AI will spit out the answer in you know
in few seconds. example, code example,
what it is, basic syntax, you know,
code, simple examples, then how it works
internally, common use cases, why eval
is almost always a bad idea, it tells
you. Okay, then uh classic dangerous
example and safe alternatives. Okay, if
you don't use eval but you want some
kind of meta programming, what can you
do? Okay, you alternative save
alternatives slightly, you know. So AI
generate this in you know in few
seconds. Amazing.
So that's that's what I'm saying and uh
and also I'm saying that I started. So
what can you do? you know,
I can read it and I can try to edit it
and like rewrite you like rephrase it so
it appears like my tutorial, but it
doesn't I mean there there's some like
styling like the the styling of the
phrasing and some parts I would you know
I would of course I would write
differently
but it doesn't matter it doesn't matter
much like like I would spend like an
hour like few hours you know practically
speaking
to rewrite this in my in completely my
style. It will take few hours to reward
it and reorganize and rephrase and
change perspective on you know some of
these AI generated output but the end
result doesn't does not matter that much
because well it matters a little bit but
however I have to spend hours to rewrite
it that's not worthwhile. So today I you
know I kind of just accepted AI output
for my tutorial. Okay that's what I
wanted to say.
Uh okay nobody's here. Yeah
she
you see the center of camera is here but
it uh okay so let's see. Yeah that's
right. That should be the center. But
why is it seems
screwed?
Oh, that's why because I have clipped,
you know. So, because part of the
camera's output is hidden on the edge of
the view. That's why it seems like not
centered.
Okay, that's one shot of Rome. We're
going to have another shot in like 15
minutes or so. Okay, that's about
evolve. Okay, JavaScript and how I
finally accepted AI output. You know,
it's inevitable. AI is changing
humanity. Like right now, nobody know
what's going on. Everyone is guessing.
There's a lot, you know, uh AI
researchers from AI corporations. Some
of them are new founders like like
currently there's one from China whose
name goes by Ki Kiwi something or
something Kim or you know supposedly you
know young genius who created something
beats on enthropy or whatever you know
it's going on every every month it's
changing you know lots of drama
and he's got views oh I think you know
new views about AI but it's all [ __ ]
okay these people and well I don't
actually know that guy but a lot of
people are talking about him and and and
others and others. Okay. So what's going
on with AI is no nobody actually knows.
That's what I want to tell you guys.
Okay. In my opinion because I
I'm fairly intelligent. I I you know AI
is something I deeply interested since
1990s. Okay. So AI so everyone is
talking about like AI is this or that.
That's all [ __ ] because including
those AI researchers and AI pioneers,
okay, there's quite there's quite a few
AI pioneers, they for example, they
created the algorithm they made many
innovations in the neuronet network um
algorithm. Okay, like there's uh Paul
Hinton, you know, there's a Brit I think
British guy. I think he's a great um
anyway there's quite a lot and some of
them are like you know questionable
quite quite questionable
so this there's a lot AI pioneers and AI
coders like for example they work at
open AI they work for Elusk they open at
these AI companies you know they are the
main you know let's say main engineers
writing creating the guac or whatever
and [snorts] they they are also
computers scientists there are um you
know or general generally scientists you
know they all all got opinions about AI
they're going to tell you oh AI is this
or that you know but but but I I want to
tell you they you know nobody actually
knows okay right now they are all like
everything you hear is like all guessing
about the future of AI what's AI able to
do or what you know it's all guessing
so that's what I want Interesting. Okay.
So, let me magnify my printer so you can
actually read.
Okay.
So, uh you know I posted a lot today uh
mostly about JavaScript you know. So
what I'm doing with JavaScript is that
you see
very interesting JavaScript you know now
you have 30 years I I did a tremendous
work on JavaScript history. Uh did I
talk about it few days ago? So like if
you go to um JavaScript history, okay,
I'm digressing over but let's go to
JavaScript blog. Okay, and actually I
think uh a few episode ago we you know
the main topic is JavaScript history. So
I worked a lot on JavaScript every day.
So let me show you uh some of them.
Oh my god, it's hot.
It's getting hot, California.
So, let's have some of these power
juice, shall we? This this uh this is
energy drink from Costco.
So I wrote a new article, the ugly
JavaScript. Yeah, I I don't think I told
this told this story in live stream. So
I wrote a new article few days ago. the
ugly JavaScript 2010 to 2026
where I tell the story of the JavaScript
community you know basically starting
with NodeJS
it's quite ugly you know like basically
JavaScript and the entire JavaScript
community and technology like React all
the frameworks the mpm it's basically
[ __ ] okay it's like like like the worst
worth worthless the worth worst [ __ ]
JavaScript. Okay. the the React, the
framework, the libraries, the [snorts]
CommonJS, the MPM, the you know, then
the TypeScript, it's all like [ __ ]
Okay, it's like worst [ __ ]
you know, like for example, let's
consider TypeScript. You know, if you
are a JavaScript developer, you you you
probably think that Typescript is
fantastic. It's necessary. It's one of
the greatest technology because it you
know it it lets you have types type
checking you know in JavaScript finally
you need it because when you when your
code you know when you have thousands of
lines of code you need you kind of need
it. Okay that's true but the thing is
JavaScript you know so so you you have a
language then you have a you need
another tool because your JavaScript is
[ __ ] it's worst [ __ ] So, so you you
have to have another guy who created
like a TypeScript, you know, like like a
superset of programming language to pile
on your [ __ ] so that so that so that it
fixed one problem of the type checking.
That's what happens. You see, you know,
to to to you a practical guy, you think
you just think, oh, TypeScript is great.
Oh, React is great. It finally solved
the problem of of manipulating dome or
whatever. [ __ ] But you don't know but
but but if you look if you can design
from scratch the dome
actually you know things just happen in
the world. So lots of things almost
everything sucks. That's by nature.
Okay. You you can't
you almost cannot you can never have a
master plan
because if you have a master plan to
begin things usually they don't go
anywhere. So the way things happen in in
life it's just that
you know you you you you you end up you
know you know in one view you just have
lots of [ __ ] you know that's the way
things happen naturally. Okay. But
anyway, so you got React, you got the
Vue, you got, you know, competing
frameworks like Angular, uh, React View,
and NextJS and SWEL, you know, like
just it's just a [ __ ] because they are
all [ __ ] trying to fix [ __ ] This
JavaScript [ __ ] created in 10 days [ __ ]
Okay, a mistake back in 30 years 30
years ago 1995. Okay, that's that's what
JavaScript is. Okay. So you so you end
up so what so what it end up doing is
that for you know millions of people we
programmers we just waste time to learn
about the esoteric technical details of
the JavaScript crap you know like okay
so for example you know you started to
have because the JavaScript no library
you started to have um you know in the
beginning nojs then because of the
common um JS library there's no library
system so someone has to invent it oh my
god this saved my day common JS you know
required require so but then that
created that created a whole bunch of
problem that created uh because that
created bundler problem uh like lots of
bundlers browser and webpack or trying
to fix it because you it doesn't have
require in browser process. So you need
to like bundle them into one file. The
the bundle of [ __ ]
Okay. [snorts]
Because just because JavaScript doesn't
have library module system in the
beginning. So you got then then the
browser the then then you got the
because the the require AMD I mean the
common JS is mostly designed for the
JavaScript as a backend server. So it's
not useful. It's not, you know, it's not
like very good for the front end. So
they have AMD
a synchronous module system for
JavaScript. Then you know so that you
created another module system
incompatible. Okay. So you got common JS
module system. Okay. Then then you got
okay you go down then you got the AMD
module system beginning in 2009.
actually they they begin the same year.
This these are communitydriven. Okay.
But then so but so NodeJS started to
support them but it doesn't work in
browser. Browser doesn't support require
[ __ ] So then you have to have start you
started to have the bundler you know
like the JavaScript bundle bundler like
a bunch of them. Um
okay I'm digressing all over. [ __ ] um
bundlers. Okay. So start start with
browserify
webpack and and I think more um okay but
webpack is most popular but today
webpack is waning is like there's uh
more replacements. Okay. So anyway I've
been doing a lot of this revisiting
because I was never I was not in this
community. So I for a long time for for
for 15 years it puzzled me like what
what what what is react what what is the
web pack what do they do like what do
you need them what what is commonjs I
didn't know okay but beginning from you
know in the past two or three years I
started to look into so I now I have a
very good idea I know exactly you know
their history okay so common js you know
common js system.
But you see what's interesting is that
in 2015 the JavaScript standard they
created they finally created a module
system but it's incompatible with the
common JS node NodeJS incompatible and
incompatible with the AMD system. So you
see JavaScript
if you know finally in 2015 they have a
module system but not compatible with
Node.js JS not compatible with the AM
andD uh you know so [snorts]
so so that's that's why I say you know
so the JavaScript so and and and
let me tell you okay so the JavaScript
module system I did a video tutorial
about module system about maybe three
month ago okay look look up my video
YouTube you'll see it but the you see
the egg script 2015 module system is
very complex. It's like a [ __ ] in the
ass
like someone got [ __ ] in the ass.
Okay, that's that's that's reality, you
know. Oh, finally. So, you know, we have
module system in JavaScript, but it's
it's a [ __ ] up [ __ ] Okay, that's what
happened. That's what it is because the
very complex very extremely complex like
like there's no programming language
whose module system is more complex than
than the JavaScript. [ __ ] Not even
considering the common JS in NodeJS or
the AMD. You just consider the you know
the the spec the official JavaScript
ECMA module system. You got, you know,
like you, you know, you got default
export, then you got named export. [ __ ]
their ass. [ __ ] their ass. Why do they
have that? Because of convention.
because by practice you know many
modules already has a default export you
know because of the NodeJS because of
the common JS you know it's so it's you
know then you know so it's then then
they had to create like variety of
syntax you know one syntax is not enough
oh why why don't we do another you know
we can also do it this way because some
people like it that way some people like
it you know so we're going to have both
the [ __ ] idiots. Okay, JavaScript
committee, you know, TC39.
What can you do?
Worse than Python. Okay, Python is bad
enough, but at least it's like one
single [ __ ] who just said, you know, but
but JavaScript, [ __ ] the JavaScript.
So you got you see you got these three
like mutually incompatible
module system in JavaScript. That's what
happens. Okay, that's what happens. So
you know so so so that's why I'm writing
I wrote this tutorial
I mean this essay the ugly JavaScript
2010 to 2016. So you need you know you
need JavaScript library then the NodeJS
got created you got the a sync [ __ ] a
sync
a pain in the ass you know like promise
promise a sync you know back then I
don't understand actually I still do not
fully understand it you know the the
from a computer science fundamental
point of view
uh and I tried to have you know it's a
bit complicated because JavaScript is
single thread okay so it's um anyway so
anyway JavaScript 2009 nojs you started
to have the async introduced by Ryan D
Ryan is a great guy and a genius okay
anyway he introduced a sync and a sync
is like a pain in the ass
like you know it's it's like a novel
idea in programming a pain in the ass to
this today. Um
it's it's just no good. Okay. You know,
then uh yeah, so JavaScript doesn't have
a library system we talked about. Uh by
the way, that was the same situation
with PHP. You know, PHP from 1995 to
2009, it doesn't have a library module
system. Okay? And and to this day, the C
programming language [ __ ] the C
programmer [ __ ]
That's the worst. That's a granddaddy.
To this day, they don't have library
system, you know. They don't have
module, you know. They just include [ __ ]
the C idiots.
Okay, time for another drink.
[sighs and gasps]
Ow. Ouch. Ouch.
Ouch. Hurt my hands.
So, how long have I been talking? Is it
an hour already?
Uh, let's see.
One concurrent viewers. Let's see. Um,
30 minutes. Okay, I've been talking for
30 minutes. Okay, not too bad.
Oh god.
You know, I was going to install Rust
today. So, yeah, I wanted to tell you
about it, but I got digressed.
So, anyway, let me finish about
JavaScript. So, MPM then MPM got
created. it's the worst you know
corporate greed. So anyway, so because
of the JavaScript library system and
browser doesn't support common JS. So
that's when you created the situation
you need you need you started to have
package managers okay which is needed by
every programming language for example
pearl the earliest one is pearl from
CPAN okay because that's that's when you
have a centralized
repository of all libraries so whenever
you need something in the programming
language you can lookup in that
centralized you know uh repository.
Then that evolved into a package manager
so that so that it's not just a
centralized library website but you also
have commands that allows you to search
you know that database or install stuff.
So you you know that's a concept of
package manager. So in JavaScript we got
power
and then mpm they are separate because
you see mpm was designed in the
beginning mpm from nodejs that was
originally designed to be javascript on
the back end as a server programming
language you see but but JavaScript is
you know primarily used for the in the
front end. So that's different. So in
the beginning you got the power library
system I mean the repo. Okay. So let me
so I started to document this. Uh so let
me show you. Okay. So where is it?
Package managers. Okay. So you know
there it is. It's dead today. You know
you don't use it today but power is from
Twitter uh mega corporation. They
created power 2012. Okay. Package
manager.
uh then you know so I asked AI you know
when power.io IO created when is it
created and why is it popular? So you
know 2012 to 2017
why is power created when there is
what's npm you know AI answer because
npm is more designed for the uh
javascript or for server while power
handles different things for the front
end such as um
such as like um you know CSS and images
and other things. Okay. So anyway, AI
answered the question. So npm created
2010 from NodeJS. Then there's Young
because MPN sucks. Got problems. So
Young from Facebook,
another mega corporation greedy. So they
created um
uh they they they uh they created Yang.
Okay. Trying to fix some problem of MPM.
Then you got um
Yeah. Then you got the you got more, you
know. Then you got PMPM,
PMPM,
then you got um so anyway, so you got
this uh
package managers. Okay, let's go back.
Uh let's go back.
Um
then you got runtime platforms. NodeJS
obviously and no antenno, my favorite.
Um let's go back. Then you got package
managers. You got bundlers. Okay.
Browsify is dead today but that kind of
begin it I think. Webpack. Okay. Let's
go back.
Uh then you got bundlers. You got UI
frameworks. That's that's where things
get interesting. You got BackboneJS.
You got AngularJS. You got EmberJS.
Those are the early ones before 2010.
Then you got React, you got Vue.
Uh then you got Angular 2, Spelt,
Nex.js,
Nux.js,
AlpineJS.
Oh, I didn't know there's a NXJS.
The equivalent full stack framework for
Vue.js providing SSR and static
generation capabilities. Oh Jesus.
What?
Let's see.
Oh, the full stack view framework. Who
Who began it?
Cheers.
Okay, next in 100 seconds they got a
video. Can you know in only in 100
seconds really? Can you watch it?
Uh,
okay. So, whatever. Okay.
So, whatever. So, I think let's stop now
because I wanted to do something else.
Okay. I want to install Rust.
Uh yeah, so I was just telling you guys
about this ugly JavaScript
uh story or article I wrote. Okay.
Okay. So today's talk show, let's go
there, paste a link there. So,
[sighs]
okay.
Okay. So, that we talked about and uh
let's see what else.
Oh, yeah. There's interesting things. Um
there's interesting things prototype JS
there's also interesting thing uh I'm
going to skip okay I want to install uh
Rust okay so let me install Rust
new
chat please and magnify
Start talking.
Allow.
Cheers.
I want to install the Rust programming
language on Windows. Should I install it
on just on Windows or should I install
it inside WSL? Which is better?
Start with native Windows. It's simpler
and what Microsoft and the Rust team
recommend for most people. Install the
MSVC build tools first. Then run the
Rust Up installer from rusty lang.org.
Use WSL only if you're targeting Linux
servers or need Linux specific tools.
Both can run side by side if your needs
change.
Thank you. Is Rust running better on
Windows or on Linux?
Linux runs Rust noticeably faster. A
2026 test showed Fedora executing the
same Rust code about 30% quicker than
Windows 11. Compilation is also faster
on Linux or WSL, often nearly twice as
fast as native Windows in benchmarks.
Runtime differences come down to the OS
kernel and file system, not the language
itself. If your work is mostly on
Windows apps, the gap may not matter
much.
Okay, let's go install Rust.
Let's see what happens. Rust programming
language. Why am I doing it? because um
you see I'm into functional programming
and Rust is predominantly you know a
functional programming language. Uh but
what I don't like about Rust is that it
is uh you know it's got the manual
memory management. There's no automatic
memory man, you know, there's no
automemory management. So-called garbage
collector by the C and C++ [ __ ] I
despise them very much about the manual
memory management and the obsession of
it. So I don't like it, you know. I
don't want any, you know, I don't want
this manual [ __ ] I want, you know, I
want high high level mathematics. I
want, you know, the mathematics that
rules them all. I don't want the bit
diddling, you know, the C C++ [ __ ]
So, I don't, you know, I don't I'm not
excited about ROS, especially because
because I have a Go programming
language, you know. So, let me show you,
you know, I I studied Go. So, check out
my Go programming language. It's it's
the best one, okay? It's the most
practical mathematical and simple Go
programming language and it's a it's you
know it's the most simple language
simpler than Python than JavaScript by
by by far simpler than Ruby okay it's
very simple you learn it you can learn
the entire thing in like two days two
days or one day like one one day or
three days you can learn the entire Go
programming language and it's the most
powerful. Okay, it's created by Rob
Pike, a well-known, you know, uh the the
the most, you know, one of the most
famous accomplished programmer Rob Pike
and and and friends. Okay, Rob Pike, a
unique guy.
So, I like it very much. But then but
then you you know you you often see on
the web people attack Goland but they
promote Rust because oh Rust Goland is
automatic memory management garbage
collection. They they hate it you know
the the the [ __ ] idiots. They like
the manual you know the go you know
memory management. So I never liked you
know I don't think I liked Rust
um
because you know so then and but then
eventually I learned Rust is is you know
Rust is basically a functional
programming language based on Okamo.
Okay, I have a lot articles about that.
You can search my web. Um, okay. So, let
me search you know. So, let me just uh
show you
uh so search web. So, go versus uh rust.
Okay. For example, I have an article on
go versus rust where I ridicule one of
the online
rust fanatic [ __ ]
That's very common. You know for example
this YouTube they will say go Goland
versus Rust HTTP REST API in Kubernetes
performance benchmark.
Typically what they say is that almost
all the same. Okay. All the like almost
every article or online opinion about go
versus Rust. We all say that Rust is
better because Rust got manual garbage
collection. Okay. They they hate Goland
and they think it's slow. these
[ __ ] from C and C++ mentality. I so
much despise them, you know, but they
forgot in order to learn Goland, you
know, like if you learn Goland for one
month compared to the same same guy your
you learn Rust for the for one month,
you can write Golan far more productive
than you can do with Rust because Golan
is very simple.
You know the simplicity of design that's
critical you know like you don't have to
oh by the way comp complicated oh if you
do this you need that flag turned on and
that flag has dependencies on that and
that you need to know this like a real
man programming language like the C C++
[ __ ]
okay so but a lot of people you know
they they like rust you know it's almost
in inevitably
the same opinion.
They don't like they don't like Goland,
you know, but they always like rust.
It's faster and so on. Okay. So, I
despise them. They they they don't, you
know, because they fail to consider
simplicity is the most important
one of you know one of the most
important element in programming
language. Okay.
So, Goland you can learn
in one day and in fact you can master
like like literally master in one week
follow my tutorial okay on sulli.info
pain info
but you know so but any but you know
people's you know say go let you know
they like rust you know this these
people you see let me read what I said
you see in this article this this is
exactly the type of coder I despise.
First of all, note that you can master
the entirety of Golola in one week if
you are a professional coder with
experience.
Rust on the other hand is five to 10
times more complex.
It also means given equal learning time
the programmer with Rust will have more
bugs. Okay, that is true.
You know time don't go to you magically
you know you have to learn something you
know you have one month experience or
two month experience or one year
experience with Goland or Rust. Okay but
the the people with Goland with just one
month experience you can do much better
but the if you the same time you spend
with Rust you have bugs
you have problems you have crashes.
Okay. But this these [ __ ] they
don't know. They never thought of it.
Typically, I attribute these people like
the C C++ [ __ ] Okay. They are the
like the they are the virus of the
computing industry.
>> [sighs]
>> Is the fan making noise on the
microphone a little bit?
C and C++ fuckets.
Okay. So I I so rust did not have a good
impression on me because it's infested
with this
uh garbage collection manual garbage
collection [ __ ]
Okay, that's my original impression.
And plus Golan is created by this Rob
Pike. I came to respect Heidi Rob Pike.
He has done lots of things such as
created he created the UTF8
um in coding among other things. He's a
big Unix fan. Okay,
Rob Pike um you know so let me let me
give make sure to give credit to other
people not just Rob Pike. Okay, Rob Pike
is most famous
creator of the Go language, but the but
it's uh it's not just him. Okay, so uh
designed at Google by Robot Gizma,
Grisma, Raike and and Ken Thompson.
Ken Ken Thompson of course is very
famous you know the guy who created C
[laughter] age 83 he's still like alive
and kicking amazing I don't like him
okay well I mean I like you know you
know you know he's a great I suppose
he's a
you know a computer engineer but I never
liked the things he created like the C
fuckets the C programming language
idiots. Okay. Anyway,
oh, okay. So, he's also he he he he and
Rob Pike together created UTF8. Okay.
And he created Grap. [laughter]
Okay. I mean, okay. So he's a good um
yeah I suppose you know engineer but the
so what so what I say is that his style
he's you know the pattern of his
thinking I don't like okay I don't like
the things he create like the C mostly C
and Unix
okay so there's another guy who is
creator of the go language Robert uh
Grymer okay I don't know him too much. A
Swiss Swiss computer scientist. He's
best known for his work on Go
programming language. Okay.
Okay. It's interesting.
Okay. So, Goland. So, rust. So, we were
talking about rust, right? So I don't
have a good in impression of Rust but in
the past you know this year I started to
look. So Rust is actually a functional
programming language and it is based on
Okamo which I consider the the best
programming language like from even the
1970s. Okay. Meta language
standard meta language SML then camel
then Ok camel then F they are the same
family okay of the meta language and
that meta language design the thinking
is just superb okay
so I highly respect okamel you know or F
and I'm trying to learn F today but I
but I learned that Rust is Actually you
you know you could say Russ is one of
the family you know it's a member of the
Okamo branch it's because it's mostly
it's mostly based on Okamo okay
functional programming supreme in fact
rust is more functional than this my you
know you know which I've been coded for
15 years more functional than this okay
But you know, but still you got this
garbage collection thing like the, you
know, bit dling [ __ ] I don't want it.
But then, but I realized, you see, you
read, you know, you look at the
computer, you know, you you you realize
that um
JP Singh,
hello. Hello. So you realize that
all functional programming languages has
or camel, F
uh or including lisp or including
Mathematica, you combine them,
their user is like 10 times less than
Rust. So Rust is actually the industrial
giant and it is right now in a position
to wipe out C and C++.
My
hatred. Okay. So I I despise the C and
C++ [ __ ]
but Rust is right now having a war with
them like consider like wiping them out
in a computing industry.
And if you consider all program all
functional programming languages this P
hascal or camel f uh wam language
mathematica closure you combine them
they are like 1% of rust
popularity
so rust is you know so so in in other
words even though I you know I I you
know I don't like the rust you know
memory you know manual memory
obsession
but you have to consider it you know
it's it's far more powerful you know
popular and powerful okay so that's why
I'm
I'm now I'm now learning Rust okay I
want to learn Rust
uh so you know part of the reason is
that you know just just just to have a
look because I actually never
have I never had any experience with um
with a programming language that does
not have garbage collection such as C
and C++
you know 30 years ago I might have wrote
you know one hello world like 30 years
ago that's it
so I never had any experience with
uh manual memory management programming
language. So for even just for curiosity
you know for the sake of computer
science
that is the reason you know I'm getting
a uh I'm going to look at rust. Okay. So
we're going to install it now.
Uh okay. So let's see
a language powering everyone to build
reliable and efficient software. Okay.
Uh let's see why is why why is the page
like looking idiotic
like can we um can we shrink it a little
bit? Okay. Get started. Let's click
installing Rust. Uh try Rust without
installing. Okay. Download Rust in it.
Next. So, which one?
Uh, this one 30 bit
X64.
Okay. These are always like kind of
idiotic
like you have to know what is your
machine. Is your machine 32bit or x64
or ARM 64? What the [ __ ] does do they
mean? [laughter]
This typical of these C++
[ __ ] you know, they are they are
they they are this idea are natural to
them. What's wrong with you know what's
wrong with you? It's so natural 32 bits
x x64 arm 64. These [ __ ] idiots I
despise so much all my life because they
are, you know, because so why why is
this bad? Because these are
incomprehensive
nerd, you know, idiot, you know, idiocy.
You are trying to, you know, you are
trying to tell the programmer about like
specific hardware. I don't give a [ __ ]
I don't care. I just want to reinstall
Rust on my Windows machine.
But they but these idiots like they have
to say, "Oh, 32bit
x64
uh ARM 64." [laughter]
Of [snorts] course, they expect you to
know the CPU architecture and you know
what whatever you know the [ __ ]
Uh [sighs] okay. So, okay. I'm I'm
rambling. Try Rust. Try Rust without
installing. What the [ __ ] is that? Oh,
web B web based.
Um, Rust. That's good. That's good.
Okay. But I want to install it. Okay.
So, x64. Let me just do that.
Now, do you have a like stand alone? I
don't want the installer. Okay. which
which may do like random things to my
system.
You have chosen to open. No, I just
cancelled it. What?
You have chosen to open rust up init.exe
which is exe file 9.5 megabytes.
Would you like to save this file? No.
Cancel.
Okay. So what are we
um
is Rust up to date? So let me look at
the state of the art of the Rust
installation page is you know did they
do this page correctly? Do you know is
it good quickly set up a Rust
development environment and write a
small app?
Okay, install Rust. Okay. So, okay.
Anyway, let's try that. 12 megabytes
rust init.exe.
Um,
okay.
Okay. Save the file.
Is Rust up to date? Rust update very
frequently. If you have installed Rust
up some time ago, chances are your Rust
version installed update. Get the latest
version of Rust by running Rust update.
Okay. Learn more about installation.
Okay.
Cargo, the Rust build tool in package
manager. Okay.
When you install Rustub, you also get
latest stable version of the Rust build
tool. Okay. Read the cargo book. Okay.
Other tools VS Code
Emacs. Oh, there there it is. My love uh
Emacs R support is available in many
editors. Okay, Emacs. What? So, what you
going to say? Emacs ROS mod. Okay. Now,
I have to install ROS mod.
Uh describe function
ROS mode. So, what do we have? Ros mode
is a autoloaded interactive. So it's
already there but um
uh arg list is not available in until
it's loaded. Okay, it's already there
but
anyway so
okay so let's go to download directory
rust open file.
Oh [ __ ] I made a mistake. I didn't want
to open file. I want to open the
directory. Okay. It looks like you have
an existing ROUB setting file at what
Russ will install the default tool chain
specified in the settings file instead
of the one inferred from the default.
ROS visual C++ prerequisites.
This requires a linker in Windows API
library, but they don't seem to be
available. What?
These components can be acquired through
a Visual Studio installer. Quick
install. Oh, God. I want to cancel. The
[ __ ] I made a mistake. Okay,
I made a mistake clicking this uh
showing folder. So yeah, I made a
mistake clicking open file.
[sighs]
Exit. I don't want anything. Can Can you
exit? Ctrl D doesn't work. Selection
option one, two, three. What?
Exit.
You know, it doesn't make me exit. What
the [ __ ] is this?
Okay, you need Ctrl C. Ctrl C. There it
is. Okay, so now let's go to the
download directory because I have full
control what I'm doing. What? No, not
that. Not that. Okay. So, download open
download directory.
Okay. So, what you want is this. Uh,
what is this? Yeah. download. Okay.
Where where the [ __ ] is Rust? What?
Rust in it.
Uh, search for Rust in it. Yeah. Okay.
So, let me show it again. Wait.
Control C.
What the [ __ ] I pressed the wrong key.
[ __ ]
Okay. Showing desktop. That's why. Okay.
So, there it is.
So what was I doing? So I think uh
desktop.
What the [ __ ] is am I doing?
So there is the rust. Okay. But um but
what was I doing?
>> [sighs]
>> Okay, let's run Rust. Okay, so we are
running Rust. It says it says Rust
visual C++ prerequisite. It says I
already have a rust up settings.
What the [ __ ] I don't remember I ever
have a rust up. Let's go there. Okay, so
rust up settings version 12. What the
[ __ ]
I don't know who. Delete it. Okay,
delete it. And Ctrl C to exit.
Okay. Now go to
download again
open the directory and now run it.
What the [ __ ] Why? Why is it still says
that users
settings? I thought I delete that. [ __ ]
It created again. What?
What? Okay.
Ctrl C to quit. Delete it. Make sure
refresh. So you see it's deleted. Okay.
Okay. So what does this do? Close that.
Open the folder. So you can see the file
is deleted. Now to be sure, let's you
know just delete it completely. Okay,
not just the backup. Okay, now go to the
download directory
and uh open the directory folder. So now
let's run the rust in it. Okay, do it.
The [ __ ] idiot. It says w user rust
up settings.comtome.
Looks like you already have existing r
setting file. No, I don't. You [ __ ]
idiot. Rust up will install the default
tool chat. No. Okay. So, they got a
mistake. Some somehow they got mistake.
So let let me you know so okay I'm just
going to be stubborn.
Okay I don't have you know they they
created this file. [ __ ]
So close that. Close that.
Now let me delete the folder. Now maybe
it's the folder that's [ __ ] up. Okay.
Delete the entire folder. So I don't
have the rest of folder anymore. Okay.
Now open the download. And now run it.
It says the same thing now. Is it
because the cash? What the [ __ ] is going
on?
[ __ ] rust. Okay.
Cheers.
You know this this this is this is just
wrong. It looks like you have a
you know it says it looks like you have
an existing roster settings but I don't.
Why is it lying? Is it you know or is it
something wrong?
Let's make sure. Okay. Rust up settings.
You created
you see you created. I don't have it.
You delete it. Okay. Delete it. You see?
Delete it. I don't have that directory.
Okay, you created now. Let let me let me
let me uh be sure. Okay. Ctrl C to
close. Refresh. Now search for Rust.
Okay. There's no Rust directory anywhere
in my
in my home directory. Okay.
Refresh. Search for Rust. Doesn't
happen. Okay. Now go to the download. Go
to the download.
Uh, search for Rust. There it is. Rust
up. Now open that.
Okay. So now it says again, you looks
[clears throat] like you have an
existing Rust. No, I don't. [ __ ]
Now let me ask AI. Okay.
You see I don't want to um
so let me ask a control J new question.
Why does Rust say I have existing rust
config
but I don't
paste why does rust up.exe
exe say I have existing rust config.
Okay.
Answer.
[sighs]
This is a known and somewhat recent
quark bug in Rust in it on Windows. What
the [ __ ]
Bad impression. Okay. Bad impression
from the Rust people.
[ __ ] idiocy.
The installer creates the settings.tomo
tommo file early in the process as part
of setting up the configuration then
immediately checks for an existing one
and prints that warning.
[laughter]
What idiocy? Okay.
[sighs]
Okay. So, what you what to do next?
Let's see. Um
okay let's I suppose I can continue
let's see
uh instead of the one inferred from the
default what what rest up will we
install the default tool chain
rust visual C++
prerequisite
Why? Why are you mentioning C++? And why
do you need C++?
Bad impression. Okay. What the [ __ ] I'm
installing Rust. I don't want C++. [ __ ]
Rust requires a linker in Windows API
libraries, but they don't seems to be
available.
Requires a linker.
That's your problem. I'm installing
Rust. Solve your [ __ ] own problem.
That's not my problem. [snorts] This
components can be acquired through a
Visual Studio installer. [ __ ] idiocy.
I don't want any Visual Studio. [ __ ]
Okay. The Rust.
Okay. So far
uh my impression of Rust is not very
good. Okay, this [ __ ] rust up [ __ ]
Quick install via the visual studio
community installer free for individuals
academic use. [laughter]
[ __ ]
You see, I don't want anything to do
with Visual Studio,
you know. I want to install Rust, but
what the [ __ ] are you trying to tell me
something about Visual Studio? And then,
oh, by the way, it's free for
individual. Go [ __ ] yourself.
Then it says manual manually install the
prerequisites for enterprise and
advanced users.
Don't install the prerequisite.
[ __ ] I don't like it.
Uh if you are targeting the GNU AVI,
what the [ __ ] is Gabi? I don't know.
So anyway,
so I think my impression of Rust
wasn't good. You know, this installer
very bad impression.
So
maybe
cheers maybe not installing Rust after
all.
So let me ask AI what is GNU ABI
>> [sighs]
>> I'm installing Rust on Windows And it
tells me something about GNU ABI. What
is GNU ABI?
GNU ABI on Windows means the calling
convention and binary format used by the
GCC compiler and mining GW toolkane.
Rust offers two Windows builds. the
recommended MSVC version that works with
Visual Studio and most native Windows
software and the GNU version for interop
with mining GW or MSYS2built C
libraries. If you're just starting out
and don't need to link against GNU
compiled code, stick with the default
MSVC installer.
Okay, you see my impression of ROS so
far is very bad. It's [ __ ] bit
dingling [ __ ]
You see all the advantage, you know, the
the the the reason I came to Rust
because of the functional programming or
camel is now it's like wiped out.
Uh do you do you guys see know what I
mean? You see, because I want functional
programming. Usually functional
programming stuff never
have this kind of [ __ ]
I want to install Rust because,
you know, because I'm interested, you
know, functional programming or camel
based programming language that's wiping
out C and C++
my hatred [ __ ]
Fantastic. Okay. But when I install so I
you know so first step you you you you
download this um where is it rust you
know so wait where's the rust page
what where is my rust uh homepage
yeah here right so you download the
installer
Then the installer first of all has a
bug saying that it you know it's got a
init but I don't. Then it's talking
about C++
prerequisite. What the [ __ ] is that? I
don't know what the [ __ ] is C++. I want
Rust to replace C++. Then it's going to
it's telling me something about
Microsoft product. Oh, by the way,
Microsoft Visual Studio C++ something
and you know it goes extra mile about by
by the way that for individual it's free
visual studio community installer
you know this rust idiots
then it's to you know like like multiple
choice [laughter]
multiple choice by the way so choice one
you can install via the v visual studio
community installer or manual install
the prerequisites for enterprise and
advanced users. So, so, so what am I? Am
I am I a enterprise and advanced users?
How do I determine
then three choice three don't install
the prerequisites if you are targeting
the GUI ABI? Like what the [ __ ] is ABI
[ __ ] idiots? Okay, this is what I'm
talking about. So
usually for my 30 years experience in
programming when I say this I know that
this kind of thing this kind of install
you know they came from the C and C++
like these people you know they view the
programming via the hardware they have
no idea what's going on okay so they are
telling you like the the way they think
oh by the way you need you you need
You need the RAM, this chip, and that
chip in order to install GNU ABI. What
the [ __ ] that is, I don't know.
Oh god.
Okay, let me ask AI because AI is
amazing.
So, let's ask AI. Okay.
Uh
the GNU Rust installer on Windows Rust
up is telling me about Visual++
prerequisites
and or something about enterprise and
advanced users or something about GNU
API. I don't understand. All I want is
install Rust on my Windows machine. So,
what can I do?
The easiest path is to download the
official Rustup-init.exe
from rust-lang.org
and run it. It will offer to install the
Visual C++ build tools for you if
needed. Accept that and you'll get the
recommended MSBC version that works with
most Windows software. If you want to
skip the Visual C++ stuff entirely,
choose the custom install option and
pick the GNU tool chain instead. Once
it's done, open a new terminal and type
rust C- version to confirm.
>> Okay, AI says just [ __ ] run with
choice one. Okay, choice one.
One.
Do it, you [ __ ] [ __ ] [snorts]
Oh, do you want to allow this app to
make changes to your device? Visual
Studio Installer.
[ __ ] I don't want to. But I don't have
a choice, do I?
Verify publish your Microsoft
Corporation file origin hard drive on
this computer. Visual Studio installer.
[laughter]
Jesus.
So installing Rust it's you know you you
you have to install Visual Studio
installer
required for some C++
[ __ ]
Okay. I I suppose I accept. Okay. I just
you know just be a know me. Okay. So,
don't be too weird. Just be a know me.
Everything will be fine.
So, it says now Visual Studio installer
because you know, you see, [ __ ] the
Microsoft Windows.
There's no way to enlarge it.
Visual Visual Studio installer. Before
you get started, we need to set up a few
things so that you can configure your
installation. Let's make uh
let's make a um screenshot of it. Okay.
Screenshot of the fact that this
occurred
on my machine.
Okay. Wait. You see that?
Jesus. You can enlarge it. Okay. So,
this um what
you can screenshot it either because
anyway
anyway so so before you get started we
need to set up a few things so that you
can configure your installer
Visual Studio installer. Okay. To learn
more about privacy [ __ ] Okay. Continue.
Visual Studio Installer.
[ __ ] the rust.
Getting Visual Studio installer ready.
I don't have a good impression. Okay.
uh
telling me something to install Visual
Studio installer. You see, I wanted to
install Rust, but the installer tells me
something about Visual Microsoft Visual
Studio installer.
[sighs]
Sad, you know, that that's a situation
of the programming industry, these
idiots.
So what now? Okay. So visual studio
installer
what what is visual studio installer? I
suppose it's a
you know it's basically visual in uh
visual studio installer but not
necessarily installing visual studio. So
it's a v it's a installer from Visual
Studio
for installing a bunch of things related
to Visual Studio.
Seems like what what that's what it is.
It's like a specialized installer for
Visual Studio.
Like you wonder why it exists. What you
know like Microsoft has a installer like
MSI called M MSI or something. Why? Why
is there a Visual Studio installer? You
don't know.
And this [ __ ] small window, you know,
again, it's tiny. You cannot enlarge it.
No way to enlarge it. It's a [ __ ]
idiot. [ __ ] Windows,
you know, like, oh, Windows, Windows 10,
Windows 11. We have like Metro design or
whatever this pretty boys on stage.
[ __ ]
Okay. Anyway, so Visual Studio
installed. Let let me make a screenshot
of it.
There it is. Okay. So, it's saying that
we'll install the frameworks, SDKs,
and tools that you'll need. You can add
more later using the Visual Studio
installer. Okay. Individual components.
MSVC.
VS 2022 C++
[ __ ]
x64
x86
build tools latest
incomprehensible
[ __ ]
by the industrial idiots.
Okay, it's going to install [laughter]
x64 x86
tools. Okay. MV MSVC
that stand for Microsoft Visual Studio
uh VC. What is VC? I don't know.
And then Windows 11 SDK software
developers kit
headers libraries and tools of the C and
C++
[ __ ] for developing apps that run
on Windows
um operating systems. Okay. [laughter]
Oh my god. Total space required 5.75
gigabytes. Jesus.
Jesus.
Download size 1.5. What? What? 5.75
gigabytes.
What the [ __ ] is the rust [ __ ]
doing?
So, let me get this, you know, let me
summarize the situation. You see, in in
order to r install Rust on Windows,
you need to invoke the Visual Studio
installer, which installs the MSVC
version 143
and Windows 11 SDK, which totals about
1.5
gigabytes.
Wait, download size 1.5 gigabyte but
total required space 5.75
gigabyte.
So in order to run you know to compile
Rust you need this 5.7 gigabyte of from
Microsoft C++. [ __ ] [ __ ] [snorts] the
Rust.
Okay. So what can I do? So am I going to
accept or not?
Uh I'm not sure you know actually I'm
thinking of no
because I cannot accept you know this
this rust you know this
I don't think I can accept this you know
like so you you you want to install rust
but it tells you that you need to
install
this Microsoft C++ stuff and windows
Window 11 SDK and plus you need to
install them from the Visual Studio
installer. So you have to install the
Visual Studio installer first then you
install this as a prerequisite of Rust.
So at this point I mean I'm thinking you
know what why am I doing Rust for
Rust is supposed to replace C++ first
right I don't want the tra I don't want
trash I don't want C++ first trash on my
system but Ross is telling me well you
need it
okay so uh I have to think about do I
want to install it or not uh actually
visual studio installed. Okay.
Okay. Now let's focus. Okay. Uh let's uh
focus
Windows 11
software developers kit.
So in order to install Rust, you need to
install the entire Windows
software developers kit.
That's what Rust Rustab is telling you.
Okay.
So,
and they total 5.7 gigabyte.
That's That's not small, my friend. 5.7
gigabytes.
What the [ __ ] is going on?
[sighs]
Okay. I'm 50% drunk. I'm 60% drunk.
something like that. Okay.
So you see when you are drunk what you
can do what you tend to do if you are
still trying to program is that you just
focus one thing at a time. So right now
I'm you know you don't see the big
picture but you are just looking at so
I'm right now looking at this this rust
install
this I can't I can't I I don't think I
can accept
5.7
gigabytes
prerequisite.
Okay, let me ask uh uh Gu. Okay,
Gork probably don't know because
the you know the AI
uh Okay, let me ask the question. Hold
on a second.
So right now I'm installing Rust via the
Rust app on Windows and it's telling me
to install the Visual Studio installer
is telling me I need to install MSSV
and Windows 11 SDK. Together they are
5.7
gigabytes.
What the [ __ ] is going on?
That's the Microsoft C++ build tools
plus the Windows 11 SDK that the default
MSVC Rust needs to link against Windows
libraries. It really is around 56 GB
installed. If you don't want to eat that
much space, cancel the Visual Studio
installer prompt. Go back to the Rust Up
options and choose the Genu tool cane
instead.
[laughter]
What a dilemma. Oh god. It tells me to
go back and choose the GNU
ABI [ __ ]
You know that like the GNU ABI. Well,
yeah, that's going to be something. else
because then
the gloom G+ I suppose it's a G you know
the GCC then it's like the entire
another story probably also gigabytes
uh god so okay thinking about it
so apparently the rust installer is
requiring
it's like requiring you to have C++ ++
compilers. Is that right? Looks like
Looks like it. So,
so is that true? The Rust compiler
actually requires the C++
compiler, at least on Windows.
Yes, the default MSBC version of Rust on
Windows needs Microsoft's linker and
Windows API libraries from the C++ build
tools and SDK. The Rust compiler itself
doesn't compile C++, but it hands off
the final linking step to link.exe,
which comes from that install. The Genu
version skips all of it and just needs
minw if you later want to build crates
with C dependencies.
What is the point of Rust if you require
C++ compilers?
The point of Rust is memory safety and
fearless concurrency without a garbage
collector. It doesn't need a C++
compiler to compile your Rust code. On
Windows, the default setup just borrows
Microsoft's linker for the final step
that glues your program to Windows
itself. You can skip the whole 5 GB
install by choosing the Guu tool chain
during Rust up setup.
So if I choose the GNU tool chain, what
else do I need to install?
For basic Rust programs, the Guunu tool
chain needs nothing else. Rust up
installs the linker and libraries
automatically. Many crates with C
dependencies will fail until you also
install MSYS2 with mining GW, which is
about 1.4 GB. If you just want to write
and run simple code, the guu path is the
lighter choice.
>> So again, is it better to install Rust
on WSL, the Windows subsystem for Linux?
>> It depends on what you're building. If
you want to target Linux servers or use
Linux only crates and Docker, WSL2 is
cleaner and often faster. For pure
Windows apps or the Windows RS crate,
native Windows with the MSVC tool chain
is better. You can run both side by side
without conflict.
Do you drink room every night?
Not every night. I actually only started
to drink recently. Okay.
So anyway, so am I going to install it?
Oh god, five gigabyte. That, you know,
that's actually a lot actually. I that's
something I like
that's actually something I have to
think about because that's five
gigabyte. What are they doing?
So, I have right now, you know, it turns
out, it so happens I learned that my my
main drive, the C drive, is a
um solid state drive. Okay. But it's a
slow one. It's like five, six years old,
seven years old. It's a slow one. Every
time like Microsoft installer start to
install, you know, the the Microsoft uh
what they call the the install tools.
Anyway, it runs in the background. My
computer froze
and I can see from the um from the
activities, you know, every time the
disk,
you know, whenever Microsoft installer
runs the disk usage maxed 200%. And my
my computer become
not responsive. Okay, so that's very
very painful. Then someone told me on
Twitter that is because I have this
Adata
SU630.
Apparently that's my uh the brand of my
solid state drive which is not very good
which is 6 years old something like
that. Okay. So,
so anyway, so um
so what what what what is my current
like capacity? Uh so you can see
con uh Windows E then enter to see the
information.
So you got 62 gigabytes free. Okay. So
actually I can install it.
Uh, okay. So, let's just install it. But
I want to install it on D drive. It
doesn't offer me a choice.
The [ __ ] stupid, you know, the the
the the the rust the rust up installer.
I really am not impressed. Okay, let's
just enter
what?
Okay, so now it's downloading Visual
Studio installer.
Running the Visual Studio installer.
Rust up. We'll continue once Visual
Studio installer is complete.
Okay, now check the uh drive device
information. Let's see what's going on.
CPU processes. Okay. So, it's supposedly
uh PowerShell Windows Explorer. What's
this? Windows Health.
It's very annoying.
Downloading Visual Studio installer. So,
where is Visual Studio installer?
You see another thing about Windows here
is that this task manager you cannot
enlarge it. [ __ ] the Microsoft Windows.
Like I don't understand like most people
they they they like the zoomers in late
Malay genian they they they are become
they are idiots basically actually most
people in the programming industry they
they they are not very bright so they
don't know what's you know they don't
see things so that you know for example
you cannot the fact that you cannot
enlarge
you know you cannot enlarge this task
manager. Well, you can buy Windows X um
which is for disabled people. Okay. So,
you have to press
super. So, press the window key. Press
and the plus key. Something like that.
Okay. Wait. Not there. Maybe. So, here.
Okay. Now, it's my system is super slow
there. You see you got the magnifier
magnify. You see this? So this is how
you can possibly im uh enlarge your
screen.
Okay. But but but this way so so you
have to press windows plus. Okay.
But this is not good. This is for like
disabled people use it you know once in
a while. You cannot work with your
operating system like this at all times.
So in other words, so cancel. So let me
uh window. So let me press windows minus
to windows minus to and windows zero to
cancel. Okay. So you can see magnifier
there.
Stop. Okay. Snip into a stop. Okay. So
you can see that's how you magnify. But
there's no normal way to magnify this
task manager.
There's no way. On the other hand, Mac,
the Mac OS, Apple, they are well
designed. You can always you can
magnify, you know, the the what they
call the CPU monitor. Okay. What or what
whatever is the name.
Uh
so this point about the user interface
design you can the fact that you cannot
magnify the task manager
you know you you ask all the people like
the Linux programmers like they never
they don't they don't know like our hot
dog on on forum this hot dog idiot okay
we got this guy which is you know this
guy [laughter]
is a is like prototypical
stereotype of the American
idiot. Okay. So these people they they
they they never imagine they don't see
things you know they don't know but
meanwhile they have opinions like this
hot dog guy always make fun of me on
something like he that I think he's he's
um that's one of his problem you know
he's he's his he's his he's his he's his
he's his he's his he's his he's his he's
his he's his he's his uh his he's his
he's his life flaw. Okay.
Anyway, so so you see, so anyway, so
right now I'm installing um Rust. Is it
done yet?
Jesus.
Wait, where where is the uh like
close that? Okay, so
I'm close that. Okay. So, what what are
we? Uh, Visual Studio installer. What?
Oh, wait. Did I Is that [ __ ] Do I have
to close? Um.
Oh, I have to click that.
Why don't you try Zik? One of the
comments says well zik is not another
programming language. Okay. I don't
think I'm interested because I'm
interested in rust because of the
functional programming background
because it bas it is based on okamel
that is the only reason I have interest
in rust
plus it's wiping out C and C++ you know
right now there's a big war so
okamo
extremely
good functional programming background.
That is the reason I'm interested in
Rust. Meanwhile, I'm not interested in
the memory management [ __ ]
which is what of the zig is supposed to
be. You know, the zig programming
language is supposed to be fixing
problems of C and C++ because of the
memory management safety. Okay, I don't
care a [ __ ] about that.
Because in my in my point of view, I'm
into mathematics. I'm into proof theory.
I'm into um you know this kind theory.
I'm not interested in bit diddling. So
I'm not interested in like the like how
do you fix the C and C++ [ __ ] you
know, bit diddling about the memory
management.
Zeke. Okay. I'm interested in functional
programming. So that that is my like
some interest in Rust and also because
Rust
they are wiping out you know they you
know they they are more popular than all
the functional programming languages.
Okay, I got to go have dinner. Okay, so
so let me click that. I think I missed I
forgot to install click that. That's
why. Oh, [ __ ] idiot.
Okay, I'm gonna go have dinner and uh
see you guys later. Okay, bye guys.
Okay, bye guys.
I see Hascal as well is good that no
Haskell you don't you see Hascal
the problem with Hascal is that nobody
use it you see that's why I'm
interesting rust because Rust like I I
said before you are probably here I mean
you are not here today I mean I mean you
were not here earlier so that's what I
mentioned Rust
is 10 times 100 times more user than
Hascal or camel
F lisp common dispac
lisp combined.
Okay. So you combine all the functional
programming including judia. Okay. the
best you know has or camel F
um
Julia Emac this common this scheme this
racket this you combine all the function
and closure combine their users it's 10
it's 100 times less than rust
so that that is why that that is the
power that you know got me interested in
rust okay So,
so you know, Hascal, yeah, I I really
would like Hascal taking over, but it's
not happening. Okay, that's why I'm
that's why I started to look at Rust.
So, even this, you know, even though the
garbage collectors, you know, the the
the obsession about that garbage
collecting [ __ ] I don't like.
Anyway, today's experience is negative.
Okay, pretty negative. that telling me
about C++. [ __ ]
Anyway, we'll see h what happens. Okay,
bye guys. Uh, thanks for watching. Uh,
bye.